Light at Night Harms Health, Even While You're Fast Asleep
If you tend to fall asleep with the TV or a bedside light on, add it to the list of ways you are probably harming your health without even trying.
In fact, a recent study led by Dr. Phyllis Zee, chief of sleep medicine at Northwestern University—
exposure to very dim light for just one night can raise your heart rate during sleep and lead to elevated blood sugar levels the next morning.
Prior studies have linked artificial light to health issues, but the connection between light and sleep is less understood.
According to reports, Zee was surprised to discover that physiological changes occurred even though participants reported getting good sleep.
"It's almost like the brain and the heart knew that the lights were on," she said.
In an interview, Zee gave three possible explanations.
First, light can cause awakening or arousal, but the minor changes noted didn't sync up with the high blood sugar observed in tests.
Also, effects on the body's internal clock and sleep hormone secretion were ruled out because blood tests of the 20 study participants showed there was no decrease in sleep hormone levels.
That leaves her hypothesis: that even dim lighting, through closed eyelids, activates parts of the brain that regulate the body system.
Zee's study was small and only provides a glimpse into the issue, but long-term effects are likely, according to Dr. Charles Czeisler of Harvard.
"People think as long as they fall asleep and are unconscious that it's not having physiological effects, but that's simply not true," he said.
"If you're consistently exposed to this type of thing, that's going to increase the risk of chronic diseases."
The University newspaper, Northwestern Now, shares tips from Dr. Zee: notably, if you must have light, go with amber or red/orange instead of blue or white, keep it close to the floor, and consider wearing a sleep mask.